Guide to the William John James Trustee and Financial Records, 1870 - 1939
William John James Trustee and Financial Records, 1870 - 1939
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1979-1
1.5
3
William John James (1860-1941) was College Librarian from 1891 to 1929 and Assistant Treasurer of Wesleyan from 1908 to 1929.
The William John James Trustee and Financial Records concern financial matters brought before the Board of Trustees. Notable subject groupings for these dates include Buildings and Grounds and the Carnegie Foundation accreditations. These records are not a complete collection of Trustee business, but complement other Trustees' holdings in the Wesleyan University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Transferred to the Archives in 1979 from the office of Robert Taylor, University Treasurer.
Historical Note
William John James (1860-1941) was College Librarian from 1891 to 1929 and Assistant Treasurer of Wesleyan from 1908 to 1929.
Collection Overview
The William John James Trustee and Financial Records concern financial matters brought before the Board of Trustees. Notable subject groupings for these dates include Buildings and Grounds and the Carnegie Foundation accreditations. These records are not a complete collection of Trustee business, but complement other Trustees' holdings in the Wesleyan University Archives.
According to a June 19, 1918 memo from Secretary of the Board David Downey, James was responsible for holding important Trustee documents. Most of the James administrative papers are marked copy or have been copied, many of annotations. Several documents in this collection are not represented in other Trustee collections.
Collection Arrangement
James organized his collection by either year or by subject. This arrangement has been maintained. Year listings correspond with the date ending the academic year in question.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Administration.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Board of Trustees.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Finance.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Buildings.; Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.
Related Material
Board of Trustees Records, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Subject Files
  - Charter (copy of 1831) and Amendments, 1870, 1905, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Buildings, Grounds, and Objects (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rich Hall--stacks blueprint plans (2), undated
    - Rich Hall--specifications, undated
    - Rich Hall--1922 letter from W. J. James
    - Church bells--foundry report and Stephen Henry Olin letter,undated
    - Plans of present and proposed buildings (4 copies), undated
    - Printed Buildings and Grounds report, 1913
    - Electric Light Plant figures, 1901-1904, 1906
    - President's House--appraisal of rugs and furniture, undated
    - Fisk Hall--Cornerstone box contents
    - 1918 Shanklin Agreement with city regarding street changes
    - Goodyear Ave.--Superior Court certificate of judgement
    - Scott Laboratory--valuation of apparatus, 1927
    - John Wesley bust--donation by Jennie Baird, 1920
    - Taxable property and decision of Demurrur rulings by Superior Court, 1925
    - Museum--accounting for Loper estate
    - Gustafson House--appraisal
    - Albert Johnston letters, Dec. 21st 1917, re property purchase
    - William Thayer Rich-proposal to build and donate a house to Wesleyan
    - Jennie Clarke documents (3) and letter (1) re University purchase of real estate
  - Carnegie Foundation, 1907-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subscriptions to Alumni Fund 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subscriptions to Alumni Fund 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Methodist Loan Receipts 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Historical Sketch of teh Endowment of Wesleyan University, printed for the use of the Trustees only, by Clara Van Vleck, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes handwritten index.
- Series 2. Chronological Business Files
  - 1901-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Waite professorship correspondence (2 letters)
    - Minute on the death of Dr. Hunt
    - Resolution and letter on the death of J.C. Van Benschoten from the American School of Classical Studies at Athens
    - Atwater letter re CT Agricultural Experiment Station and Carnegie Institute
    - Local and General Executive Committee Reports 30 May 1903
    - Audited Reports of Treasurer and Asst. Treasurer (2 copies)
    - Bonds list
    - Receipts and Expenditures Statement
    - Financial Exhibit-printed
  - 1903 Departmental Reports (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chemistry (Atwater 3pp) as a letter to Pres. Raymond
    - Economics and Social Science (Fisher 4pp)
    - English Language (Mead 2pp)
    - Geology (Rice 1p)
    - History (Dutcher 2pp)
    - Library-incl. financial (James 2pp)
    - Mathematics and Astronomy (Van Vleck 3pp)
    - Physics (Crawford 2pp)
  - 1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Treasurer's Report for 1904
    - Financial Exhibit-printed
  - Trustee Business, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Professor Merrill's letter of resignation
    - Library Committee--adopted regulations
    - Alumni Trustees election--Report of tellers
    - Miss Van Vleck--resolution on her retirement
    - Resolution of thanks for portrait of Mr. Rich presented by Mrs. Alice C. Bonbright
    - Joseph S. Stout--minute on his death
    - Charles Scott--minute on his death
    - Swift and Co. donation of stock
    - Commencement and Annual Exercises printed programs
    - John Bell Scott Prize (modern language excellence)
    - Walkley Prize Fund (psychology) in memory of David Hart Walkley 1857-1878
  - 1905 Departmental Reports (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Biology (Conn 2 pp)
    - Chemical Department (Bradley 7 pp)
    - Economics and Social Science (Fisher 4 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 2 pp)
    - English Literature (Winchester 6 small pp)
    - Geology (Rice 2 pp)
    - German (Fife 3 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 4 pp)
    - Latin (Merrill 3 pp)
    - Library incl. financial (James 3 pp)
    - Mathematics (Van Vleck 3 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 2 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford 2 pp)
    - Romance Languages (Kuhns 2 pp)
    - Committee on Department reports (4 penciled pages)
    - Summary (3 pp) of department reports (with accompanying 1 p note from President Raymond)
  - Trustee Business, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Executive Committee Report
    - From W.C. Fisher to President Raymond describing duties as Mayor of Middletown (25 June 1906) and schedule of mayoral engagements
    - Conn letter to Trustees re Alumni Fund
    - President's Mid-Year Report (North College fire and cost comparisons of several eastern colleges)
    - Financial Exhibit (printed)
  - Departmental Reports, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Biology (Conn 2 pp) mid-year report
    - Library (James 3 pp) mid-year report
    - Chemical Department (Professor Benedict 4 pp)
    - Economics (Fisher 3 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 3 pp)
    - Geology (Rice 2 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel, March and June, 1 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 3 pp)
    - Latin (Harrington 1 p)
    - Librarian (James 4 pp)
    - Library Committee (James 2 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 1 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford 3 pp)
  - 1907 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - James letter regarding capacity of Rich Hall, 2 February 1907
  - 1908 and 1909 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Reports B-D with envelope labeled Reports on Separate Womens' College. (Report D concerns chapel requirements)
    - Expiration of Trustee terms notification, 1908
    - David Downey letter enclosing exhibits from the Board of Trustees, referred to in the record of the last Trustee meeting. Exhibit E is noted as being elsewhere.
      - Exhibit A Endowment Securities list
      - Exhibit B Report of the Local Executive Committee
      - Exhibit C Report of the General Executive Committee
      - Exhibit D Library Committee Report
      - Exhibit F Votes cast in election of alumni Trustees
      - Exhibit G Report of the Hospital Committee
      - Exhibit H Report of the Student Body
      - Exhibit I Letter from F.W. Nicholson on new edition of the Alumni Record
      - Exhibit J Charter change advisery committee proposed
      - Exhibit K Letter from Raymond resigning professorship of English Bible and Biblical Literature
  - 1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Endowment securities list, 1910
  - 1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Honorary degree nominations
    - Shanklin letter announcing W.C. Squire honorary degree nomination by the Academic Council
    - Chapel incident and press relations letter from Frank Nicolson, 26 May 1911
    - Bylaws of the University
    - Psi Upsilon printed report
    - Report on annual faculty reports (and envelope)
    - Report of Local Executive Committee
    - Army and Navy Union
    - Alumni Trustee election results
    - President's annual report
    - Endowment securities list, 1911 (2 copies)
    - June 13 Wesleyan balance at the Brooklyn Title Guarantee and Trust Co.
    - Estimate of receipts and expenditures 1911-1912
  - 1911: Departmental Reports (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Biology (Conn 4 pp)
    - Chemistry (Bradley 2 pp)
    - Economics and Social Science (Fisher 4 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 4 pp)
    - Geology (Rice 3 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel 1 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 4 pp)
    - Librarian's Report (James 4 pp)
    - Latin (Harrington 1 pp)
    - Mathematics (Howland 1 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 2 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford & Cady 2 pp)
    - Romance Languages (Kuhns 1 pp)
  - 1912
    - Minutes of Executive Committee meeting (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Preamble and Resolution of Exec. Comm. of Alumni Council (with cover letter)
    - Proposed Amendments to Bylaw giving Executive Committee interim powers between Board meetings
    - Trustee ballot results
    - Letter of appointment and one of acceptance of faculty position of H. Lee Ward
    - Faculty Recommendations on Bachelor and Masters Degrees
    - Commons Club letter thanking Board for repairs to Foss House
    - Endowment securities October (3 c.) and June (2 c.) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Wesleyan stock certificate issue
    - Assistant Treasurer ledger worksheet
    - By-law amendment allowing Finance Committee supervision of all University funds
  - 1912 Departmental Reports (Box 2, Folder 16)
    2 copies of each.
    - Faculty Reports summary
    - Biology (Conn 3 pp)
    - Chemistry (Bradley 3 pp)
    - Econ. & Social Sciences (Fisher 2 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 3 pp)
    - English Literature (Winchester 2 pp)
    - German (Fife 5 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel 1 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 3 pp)
    - Latin (Harrington 2 pp)
    - Math (Howland 1 pp)
    - Phil. & Psychology (Dodge 2 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford/Cady 2 pp)
    - Romance Languages (Kuhns 1 pp)
    - Library (James 3 pp)
  - 1913 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Letter to Shanklin from director of Carnegie Institution Nutrition Lab conveying praise of WOA by French scientists
    - Resolution of Hartford Get-Together Club defending Willard Fisher from criticism by Press and cover letter (also acknowledgment of receipt of above by Trustees)
    - Call to October 24th Board meeting
    - Letter to Shanklin from W.G. Chanter, YMCA undergraduate representative, requesting aid for Kansas City Convention
    - Estimated budget, 1912-1913
  - 1913 Departmental Reports (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Biology (Conn 3 pp)
    - Chemistry (Renshaw 1 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 4 pp)
    - English Literature (Winchester 4 pp)
    - Geology (Rice 3 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel 2 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 5 pp)
    - Library (James 3 pp)
    - Math & Astronomy (Howland 1 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 3 pp)
    - Psychology (Dodge 1st annual report 3 pp)
    - Physics (Cady 4 pp)
  - 1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Joint meeting committee-Faculty and Finance
    - General Education board statement of reciepts
    - Telegram--W.V. Kelley regarding absence from meeting
    - East Maine Conference trustee announcement
    - Letter--Frank Mason North regarding absence from meeting
    - Executive Committee Report
    - Trustee Comm. on Faculty re Library expenses
    - Memorial minute, George G. Reynolds
    - Amount collected on Endowment, undated
    - Treasurer's Statement (also brief statement) 1914
  - Departmental Reports, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Biology (Conn 2 pp)
    - Chemistry (Bradley 5 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 4 pp)
    - Freshman Composition (Conley 2 pp)
    - English Literature (Winchester 4 pp)
    - Geology (Rice 4 pp)
    - German (Fife 4 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel 1 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 5 pp)
    - Latin (Harrington 2 pp)
    - Library (James 4 pp)
    - Math (Howland 3 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 2 pp)
    - Physical Education (Fauver 4 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford/Cady 4 pp)
  - Trustee Business, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Joint Committee of Faculty and Trustees: minutes, February 25, March 30, and June 4, 1915
    - Library Committee, binding appropriation request
    - Bylaws changes
    - Alumni Trustee election results
    - Executive Committee Report
  - Departmental Reports, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Astronomy (Slocum 2 pp)
    - Biology (Conn 1 pp)
    - Chemistry (Bradley 3 pp)
    - Economics and Social Science (Tuttle 2 pp)
    - English Language (Mead 2 pp)
    - English Literature (Winchester 2 pp)
    - Geology (Rice 3 pp)
    - German (Fife 2 pp)
    - Greek (Heidel 2 pp)
    - History (Dutcher 3 pp)
    - Latin (Harrington 2 pp)
    - Library (James 5 pp)
    - Mathematics (Howland 1 pp)
    - Philosophy (Armstrong 1 pp)
    - Physics (Crawford/Cady 3 pp)
    - Psychology (Dodge 1 pp)
    - Rhetoric (Conley 1 pp)
    - Romance Languages (Kuhns 1 pp)
    - Committee on Departments, report
  - Trustee Business, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Executive Committee Report
    - Degree recommendations by faculty
    - Salary list
    - Johnston, Albert, forwarded letter and copies of A New Assertion of College Aims and Memorandum of a Table Talk of a Few Wesleyan Alumni
    - Rice, William North, and Winchester, Caleb T., letter to Trustees declining to write a history of Wesleyan
    - Recommendation, unexpended portion of Squire monies
    - Nominations to Board of Trustees
    - Friends of the University, account of pledges
    - Endowment Securities List, June 1916
  - Trustee Business, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Budget, 1916-1917
    - Resolution, re: President Shanklin's directorship of YMCA
    - National War Work Council, appeal for President Shanklin's leave of absence
    - Salary increases (Rich, Johnston, and Governor Weeks contributions)
    - Academic Council, communication
    - Bennett Lectureship, Committee on
    - Degree certificates, faculty recommendations
    - Greek Department, visiting committee evaluation of
    - Library Committee report
    - Librarian's report
    - YMCA, letter requesting President Shanklin's service in France, and resolution of the faculty thereto
  - Trustee Business, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Library committee report
    - Coal situation report
    - Academic Council, communication to Trustees
    - Bennett Lectureship, report on
    - Executive Committee report
    - Degrees and certificates for students in war service, faculty recommendations
    - Budget, 1918-1919
    - Latin Department Visiting Committee, report on Wesleyan classes
    - Greek Department Visiting Committee, report on Wesleyan classes
    - Scheme and prices of college rooms
    - Estimated expenses, 1917-1918, 1918-1919
  - Trustee Business, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Executive Committee report
    - Finance Committee, October 14, 1918 and November 3, 1918
    - Trustee Meeting, setting fees, November 5, 1918
    - Mercier, Cardinal, honorary degree
    - Faculty and Curriculum meetings
    - Bylaws, amendment regarding quorem to make or change investments
    - Alumnus publishing appropriation
    - Minutes, Trustees, November 5, 1918
    - Wesleyan Campaign Committee
    - Estimated budget, 1918-1919, 1919-1920
  - Trustee Business, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Connecticut College, correspondence about alumnae
    - Faculty Committee report
    - Tentative budget
    - Appointment recommendations
    - Bennett Foundation report
    - College bills recommendations
    - Buckley, Dr. J. M., memoir report
    - Buckley, Dr. J. M., memorial minute
    - Executive Committee reports
    - Special Committee report
    - Annuities, resolution
    - Tuition scholarship information
    - Regulations regarding rental of college rooms
  - Trustee Business, 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Tentative budget, 1920-1921
    - Trustees Annual Meeting minutes, May 18, 1921
    - Finance Committee minutes, February 2, 1922
    - Committee on Faculty and Curriculum minutes
    - Executive Committee meetings, October 1921, January 1922, May 1922
  - 1930-1939
    - Audit reports, July 1, 1930 and December 31, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Audit reports, June 30, 1931 and June 30, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Audit reports, June 30, 1933 and June 30, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Audit report, June 30, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Audit reports, June 30, 1937 and June 30, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Student Accounts Receivable, June 30, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Undated reports (Box 3, Folder 18)